<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The humble petition of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of the city of London, in Common-Councell assembled to the Right Honourable the Lords and Commons assembled in High Court of Parliament. Whereunto is annexed, two petitions; the one entituled, The humble petition of divers well-affected citizens of the city of London. The other entituled, The humble petition of divers young-men, citizens, and other apprentices of this honourable city.</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3536</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E399_30</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201729</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899511</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899511</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153993</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86812)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153993)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2393:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The humble petition of the Lord Major, aldermen, and commons of the city of London, in Common-Councell assembled to the Right Honourable the Lords and Commons assembled in High Court of Parliament. Whereunto is annexed, two petitions; the one entituled, The humble petition of divers well-affected citizens of the city of London. The other entituled, The humble petition of divers young-men, citizens, and other apprentices of this honourable city.</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Cotes, printer to the honourable city of London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 24".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153993:1"/>
            <p>The humble PETITION OF THE Lord Major, Aldermen, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the City of <hi>London,</hi> in Common-Councell aſſembled:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>TO THE</hi> Right Honourable the Lords and Commons aſſembled in High Court of PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed, TWO PETITIONS; The one Entituled, <hi>The humble Petition of divers well-affected Citizens of the City of</hi> London.</p>
            <p>The other Entituled, <hi>The humble Petition of divers Young-men, Citizens, and other Apprentices of this Honourable</hi> CITY.</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Richard Cotes,</hi> Printer to the Honourable City of <hi>LONDON,</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petitions">
            <pb facs="tcp:153993:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153993:2"/>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE THE Houſe of Commons aſſembled in High Court of Parliament: <hi>The humble Petition of the Lord Major, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Commons of the City of</hi> London <hi>in Common-Councell aſſembled.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Petitioners have by Ordinance of Parliament, dated the 23 preſent, taken notice of the pleaſure of both Houſes, for conſtituting a new Committee for the <hi>Militia</hi> of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties thereof, and of all other places within the Lines of Communication, and the weekly Bills of Mortality, and for determining of a former Ordinance for the <hi>Militia</hi> of this City, &amp;c. dated the Fourth day of <hi>May</hi> laſt: Which being taken into ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration, the Petitioners could not but firſt cal to minde, how farre both Houſes of Parliament had formerly honored the City, when they firſt eſtabliſhed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153993:3"/>the Committee for the <hi>Militia,</hi> and ſince inlarged or altered the ſame, to take the ſenſe of this Court, before they finally reſolved thereupon; Which confidence the Petitioners are not conſcious to themſelves to have forfeited: And next being ſenſible, by two Petitions preſented to this Court, (the Copies whereof are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed) the one intituled, <hi>The humble Petition of divers wel-affected Citizens of the City of London;</hi> and the other intituled, <hi>The humble Petition of divers Young-men, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and others Apprentices of this City;</hi> what a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſtemper this ſuddain change hath already made, and may further raiſe in the City; beſides that hereby the City is for the preſent put out of all regular poſture of defence:</p>
               <p>The Petitioners could not but return unto this Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſe, and humbly and earneſtly pray, That the <hi>Militia</hi> which was eſtabliſhed by Ordinance of the fourth of <hi>May</hi> laſt, as aforeſaid, and then ordered to continue for one whole Year, may be re-eſtabliſhed; That ſo the preſent feares and diſtempers in the City may be diſperſed and appeaſed; whereunto as the Petitioners humbly conceive this to bee the onely preſent ſafe meanes, next under the mighty hand of God; ſo they wil not doubt but that the ſaid <hi>Militia,</hi> as hitherto they have done, will in all things perform their duties according to their Truſt.</p>
               <closer>And the Petitioners ſhall pray, &amp;c.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153993:3"/>
               <head>To the Right Honorable the Lord Major, the Right Worſhipfull the Aldermen and Commons of the City of <hi>London</hi> in Common-Councell Aſſembled.</head>
               <head type="sub">The humble Petition of divers well affected Citizens of the City of <hi>London;</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat whereas we have lifted up our hands to the High God, for the Reformation and defence of Religion, his Majeſties juſt power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Liberties of the Subjects, and the Priviledges of Parliament; and ſeriouſly conſidering the late tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to violate all theſe, and to weaken the zeale and forwardneſſe of this City, and this Honourable Court in the maintenance of the ſame; by indevouring to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the preſent <hi>Militia</hi> confirmed by authority of a free Parliament for a yeer, and made choiſe of by this Honourable Court: <q>In this ſtraight and exigency we are bold in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, yet with all earneſtneſſe to pray; that this Honourable Court would ſadly weigh the preſent dangers: and as in former times it hath bin your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be inſtrumentall for the preſervation of this miſerable and dying Kingdome, by the interpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your courage, power, and wiſedome in a time of need, ſo you would not ſuffer it to be buried in perpetuall oblivion and reproach by yeilding up that <hi>Militia,</hi> which by the good providence of God and the authority of a free Parliament, hath bin inveſted in your hands, the onely viſible means under God we have now left for the ſecurity of our Religion, Lives, and Liberties.</q>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>And we ſhall pray, &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153993:4"/>
               <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE The Lord Major, the Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull the Aldermen, and the Worſhipfull the Commons in Common-Councell aſſembled.</head>
               <head type="sub">The humble Petition of divers Young men, Citizens and others Apprentices of this Honorable Citie.</head>
               <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat your Petitioners being ſadly affected with the diſtractions of theſe times (wherein divers diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Perſons (for the advancement of their own Intereſts) labour to ſow new ſeeds of Diviſion and diſcord amongſt us, whereby Incendiaries are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, the well-affected diſcountenanced, the priviledges of Parliament violated, the publike Worſhip of God ſleighted, the Liberties and properties of the faithfull ſubjects of this Kingdome, and eſpecially of this City much endangered, and the long deſired for end of theſe troubles (by his Majeſties gracious compliance with, and his ſafe and Honorable returne to his Parliament, which wee hoped was almoſt obtained) now retarded, and for preſent altogether fruſtrated) have preſented their humble Petition to both Houſes of Parliament, a Copy whereof is hereunto annexed, the which they have thought it their duty, likewiſe to tender unto this Honorable Court; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confident, that as their deſires in theſe their humble Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes, ariſe from no other ends whatſoever, but, the glory of God, and the diſcharge of their conſciences, in purſuance of that ſolemne League and Covenant which lies upon them, <hi>To endeavour to their utmoſt in their places and callings, to uſe all lawfull wayes and meanes, for the conſervation and maintenance of the juſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153993:4"/>Rights and Priviledges of Parliament</hi> (lately ſo much violated;) <hi>The preſervation and defence of his Majeſties Royall Perſon and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, together with the true Religion and Liberties of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, And for the diſcovery and bringing to condigne puniſhment all evill Inſtruments whatſoever,</hi> which labour by fomenting ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe feares and jealouſies, to divide and make parties amongſt the people, thereby to retard the ſettlement of Church and State; So we doubt not but this Honorable Court (who have been Inſtrumentall to Invite us,
<note place="margin">Declaration to the Kingdome, 12 <hi>July</hi> 164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> both by example and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion (according to ſeverall Ordinances and Declarations of Parliament,) to engage our ſelves to the Proſecution of the ſaid ends,
<note n="*" place="margin">An Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for Sr. <hi>Tho. Fairfax,</hi> 15. <hi>Iuly</hi> 1644.</note> wherein you have already done very much to your everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing praiſe &amp; commendation) wil ſtill with all Reality, conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and undaunted magnanimitie, purſue the ſame, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe encourage all thoſe, that ſhall according to their duty, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to promote the ſame ends: Wherefore we humbly pray,</p>
               <p>That this Honorable Court would be pleaſed to uſe their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt endeavours, by their addreſſes to the Parliament, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, as they in their wiſedomes ſhall think fit, for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of your Petitioners deſires, contained in the above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Petition.</p>
               <p>We cannot (likewiſe) but with all thankfullneſſe take notice of what this Honorable City hath done, for the putting in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of ſeverall Ordinances of
<note n="*" place="margin">Ordinance 27. <hi>Iune</hi> 1643. Ordinance 30. <hi>Nov.</hi> 1643. Ordinance 2 <hi>Feb.</hi> 1643.</note> Parliament, That none be put into any place of truſt, either in Church or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, but ſuch as have taken, and now ſtand well affected to the Covenant, to which we are confident that you will ſtill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here.</p>
               <p>And whereas there have been and ſtill are ſeverall factious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who ſtile themſelves the well-affected of this City (though unworthy of that name) who labour to T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aduce the actions thereof, thereby to bring an Odium upon it, &amp; to lay it open to their malice; A freſh Inſtance whereof, wee have in a late Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition preſented to the Parliament, pretented to be the Petition of the Young men and Apprentices of this City; As likewiſe by a Petition pretended to be preſented to Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> the which we are ready to produce, and referre the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them to this Honorable Court. And further pray,</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153993:5"/>
               <p>That as both the <hi>Militia</hi> of this City, hath been legally cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by this Honorable Court, according to Ordinance * of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and the Common-Councell legally choſen by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Wards (according to the ancient Cuſtome of this City,) you would be pleaſed to retaine the ſame Power both Civil and Military in your owne hands. And</p>
               <p>That you would be pleaſed (for the prevention of the many Imminent dangers, to which this City may be lyable by reaſon of theſe diſtractions) to take ſuch effectual and ſpeedy courſe for the ſafeguard and defence thereof; that the feare, either of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Mutiny within, or of any unwarrantable Power from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, may in ſome meaſure bee taken away, whereby Trade (the main ſupport of this City) now mightily impaired, may be again revived, and the Franchizes and Liberties of this Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble City (to which wee are the Apparent heires) maintained and defended.</p>
               <p>And as your Petitioners are in duty bound, both by that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation which they ſtand in to the Honorable City, as by that ſolemne engagement whereinto they have entred, ſo they will be alwayes ready to hazard their lives for the defence thereof, and not ſuffer themſelves directly, or indirectly, by any terrour or perſwaſion to be drawn from their duty herein.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
